

Sichen Li

Tel: (+49)1590 1827144; Email: sli@physik.rwth-aachen.de More Info on Personal website: https://season0112.github.io/

SUMMARY: Data Scientist residing in the Netherlands with five years data research experience in performing machine and statistical models to extract actionable insights and provide solutions. Available ASAP.

SKILLS

Python, Git, Linux, C++, Bash Shell, MySQL, Data visualization (Matplotlib, Seaborn), Cluster Server, Machine Learning(Scipy, Scikitlearn, Tensorflow), Statistical Modeling(Probability Theory, Hypothesis Testing and Confidence Intervals, Analysis of Variance, Time Series Analysis, Likelihood Estimation), Data Cleaning and Processing

EDUCATION

2017.11-2023.07

PhD in Astroparticle Physics

RWTH Aachen University, Aachen, Germany / European Organization for Nuclear Research, Geneva, Switzerland

09/2015-07/2017

Master of Science in Physics

Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China

09/2011-07/2015

Bachelor of Science in Physics

Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China

WORK EXPERIENCE

11/2017-07/2023 Data Scientist, RWTH Aachen University, Aachen, Germany

- Cosmic Ray identification with Machine Learning
 - Train the classifier with machine learning algorithms (BDTs, Neural Networks, etc) on Comic Monte Carlo simulation data
 - Hyperparameter Optimisation for performance with Grid/Random Search
 - Apply the classifier to real collected data from the International Space Station, showcase a significant 20% improvement in performance compared to previous classifiers
- **Analysis of Solar Wind impact on Cosmic Rays**
 - Data Cleaning and Reduction for over **200 billion** cosmic events collected from the International Space Station
 - Apply advanced statistical models, including likelihood template fit techniques to extract antiproton signals from the collected data
 - Parameter estimation and confidence level to constrain Dark Matter models
 - Time series analysis of obtained cosmic antiprotons, identify distinct patterns in the propagation of cosmic antiprotons within the solar system for first time

11/2017-10/2022

Scientific Researcher, European Organization for Nuclear Research, Geneva, Switzerland

- Raw Cosmic Ray data calibration
 - Investigate space operation during data taking to understanding Raw Data Quality
 - Execute precise calibration procedures on raw cosmic ray data to ensure accurate measurements
 - Achieve a remarkable reduction in measurement uncertainty of the physics response, reaching within 5%
- **Detector in Space Monitoring**
 - AMS-02 is a cosmic ray detector installed on the International Space Station, which is collecting cosmic ray data in 24/7 operation. My task is to monitor sub-detectors running in space, and perform daily high voltage adjustment to optimize detector performance

09/2015-07/2017 | Research Assistant, Harbin Institute of Technology, Harbin, China

- Meson particle decay calculation
 - Using quantum filed theory model (BS equation) to numerically solve wave function of mesons, calculate particle decay widths to identify higher excited states of particle

LANGUAGE